Siu Lun Chau

Postdoctoral Researcher @ CISPA

✓ siu-lun.chau@cispa.de

L +44 7415 137484 | **G** chau999

Saarbrücken, Germany

About me

Hi, I am a postdoctoral researcher at the CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security researching at interface of economic theory and machine learning, with a focus on promoting trustworthy AI models. Previously at Oxford, Max Planck Institute, and Amazon.

Education

DPhil in Statistical Science

Oxford, United Kingdom

St.Peter's College, University of Oxford

Oct 2018 - Apr 2023

- Thesis: "Towards Trustworthy Machine Learning with Kernels"
- SUPERVISORS: Prof. Dino Sejdionvic, Prof. Mihai Cucuringu, and Prof. Xiaowen Dong.
- FUNDING: ESPRC and MRC studentship for DPhil in Statistics and Machine Learning

MMATH Mathematics and Statistics (First Class Honor)

Oxford, United Kingdom

Sep 2014 - Jul 2018

Lady Margaret Hall, University of Oxford

- RANK: 2nd in 4th year and 1st in 3rd year.
- MASTER'S SUPERVISOR: Prof. Mihaela Van Der Shaar
- MASTER'S THESIS: "Modelling Diseases Trajectories with Infinite Mixture of Gaussian Processes" (Distinction)
- UNDERGRADUATE SUPERVISOR: Prof. François Caron
- Undergraduate Essay: "Adaptive and Gradient Bossting" (Distinction)

Work Experience

CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security

Saarbrucken, Germany

Mar 2023 - Present

Postdoctoral Researcher

- SUPERVISOR: Dr. Krikamol Muandet
- Project: "Towards Trustworthy AI through Synergy between Machine Learning and Economics"

Amazon Applied Scientists Intern London, United Kingdom

Jun 2022 - Dec 2022

- PROJECT: Coherent Multi-granularity Demand Forecasting for the Transportation Service Outbound Network
 - Developed Deep Coherent Probabilistic Forecasts on the Amazon EU transportation network for logistic optimisation. Solutions are delivered into production-ready AWS infrastructure.
- Produced research best practice and software developement guidelines for the Applied Science Team.

Max Planck Institute of Intelligent System

Tübingen, Germany

Oct 2021 - Jun 2022

Visiting researcher

- SUPERVISOR: Dr. Krikamol Maundet
- PROJECT: Interface between Machine Learning and Economics
 - Researched into relaxing restrictive assumptions in Instrumental Variable Regression and examined non-parametric hypothesis testing framework for Regression Discontinuity Design.

Cambridge Spark

Cambridge, United Kingdom

Machine Learning Content Developer

Aug 2017 - Oct 2021

- RESPONSIBILITIES: Designed and delivered ML courses to up-skill students and companies. Topics covered include: ML fundamentals, graphs, model explainability using LIME and SHAP, time series forecasting, and Gaussian processes.

Oxford Strategy Group Digital

Oxford, United Kingdom

Cofounder & Managing Director

Apr 2017 - Apr 2019

- RESPONSIBILITIES: Cofounded and managed Oxford first student-led machine learning consulting group.

Research Interests

The goal of my research is to develop trustworthy algorithms for practitioners using tools from machine learning, statistics, and economics. In particular, I am interested in the following:

- Econometrics and Experimental design
- Kernel methods and Gaussian Processes
- Ranking and Preference learning

- Causal Inference
- Explainability and Uncertainty modelling
- Graph Machine Learning

Publications

Conference Proceedings

- 7. **Siu Lun Chau**, Robert Hu, Javier Gonzalez, Dino Sejdinovic, "RKHS-SHAP: Shapley Values for Kernel Methods", Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022)
- 6. **Siu Lun Chau***, Robert Hu*, Jaime Ferrando Huertas, Dino Sejdinovic, "Explaining Preference with Shapley Values", Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022)
- 5. Robert Hu, **Siu Lun Chau**, Dino Sejdinovic, Joan Alexis Glaunès, *"Giga-scale Kernel Matrix-Vector Multiplication on GPU"*, Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2022)
- 4. **Siu Lun Chau**, Mihai Cucuringu, Dino Sejdinovic, *"Spectral Ranking with Covariates"*, European Conference on Machine Learning and Principles and Practice of Knowledge Discovery in Databases (ECML PKDD 2022)
- 3. **Siu Lun Chau**, Javier Gonzalez, Dino Sejdinovic, "Learning Inconsistent Preference with Gaussian Processes", International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics (AISTATS 2022)
- 2. **Siu Lun Chau***, Jean Francois Ton*, Yee Whye Teh, Javier Gonzalez, Dino Sejdinovic, "BayesIMP: Uncertainty Quantification for Causal Data Fusion", Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2021)
- 1. **Siu Lun Chau***, Shahine Bouabid*, Dino Sejdinovic, "Deconditional Downscaling with Gaussian Processes", Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2021)

Journal Articles

1. Xingyue Pu, **Siu Lun Chau**, Xiaowen Dong, Dino Sejdinovic, "Kernel-based Graph Learning from Smooth Signals: A Functional viewpoint", IEEE Transactions on Signal and Information Processing over Networks (IEEE 2020)

Invited Talks

CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security

Title: Explaining Kernel methods and preference models with RKHS-SHAP

Saarbrücken, Germany

Feb 2023

Oxford Strategy Group Digital

Title: Introduction to Explainable ML

Oxford, United Kingdom

Feb 2023

ECML PKDD 2022

Title: Spectral Ranking with Covariates

Grenoble, France

Sep 2022

ELISE Theory Workshop on ML Fundamentals at Eurecom

Title: Explainability for Kernel methods

Antibes, France

Sep 2022

S-DCE Alan Turning Institute seminar

Title: Deconditional Gaussian Processes

London, United Kingdom

Jun 2022

UCL Gatsby Unit

London, United Kingdom

Title: Explaining Kernel methods with RKHS-SHAP

Apr 2022

UCL Statistical Machine Learning Group

Title: Deconditional downscaling with Gaussian Processes

London, United Kingdom

Feb 2022

Imperial & Oxford StatML seminar

Title: Shapley values for Model Explanations

London, United Kingdom Feb 2022

Warwick ML Group Warwick, United Kingdom

Title: Uncertainty Quantification for Causal Data Fusion

Jun 2021

Supervision Experience

Masters Students

Oscar Yung (University of Oxford)

Oxford, United Kingdom

THESIS: "Two Sample Testing for Regression Discontinuity Design" Feb 2022 - May 2022

Samuel Weinman (University of Oxford)

Oxford, United Kingdom

THESIS: "Analysis of Price-Volume Interplay in Financial Markets via Machine Learning" May 2020 - Aug 2022

Undergraduate Students

Mohammad Mehdi Mojarradi, Jihong Lee (Williams College)

Williams-Exeter Exchange Program at Oxford University

William Conyers, Daniel Park (Williams College)

Williams-Exeter Exchange Program at Oxford University

Oxford, United Kingdom

Mar 2021 - Nov 2021

Oxford, United Kingdom

Jan 2020 - Mar 2020

Teaching Experience

University of Oxford

Tutor

A12 Simulation and Statistical Programming	2020
SB1.1 Applied Statistics	2020
SB1.2 Computational Statistics	2020
SB2.2 Statistical Machine Learning	2021

TEACHING ASSISTANT

SB2.1 Foundations of Statistical Inference 2019

Awards

Sep 2018 ESPRC and MRC studentship for DPhil in Statistics and Machine Learning

Sep 2017 Department Prize for FHS Mathematics and Statistics Part B (Top of the year)

Consulting Projects

Ravio (HR Tech Startup)

London, United Kingdom

PROJECT: MONOTONIC QUANTILE REGRESSION FOR SALARY BENCHMARKING

Dec 2022 - Feb 2022

- Developed a tree-based quantile regressor with monotonic constraints to incorporate business logic and avoid quantile crossing.

Ravio (HR Tech Startup)

London, United Kingdom Apr 2022 - May 2022

PROJECT: JOB TITLE ALIGNMENT USING NLP MODELS

- Utilised pre-trained languague models such as RoBERTa and GPT3 to create word embeddings to compare and align job titles across companies to standardise compensations.

gini (Fin tech startup)

Hong Kong

PROJECT: EXPLAINABLE FORECASTING SPREADSHEET PLUG-IN

Dec 2020 - Jan 2021

- Developed a Gaussian Processes based explainable time series model using SAGE for giniPredict, a forecasting spreadsheet plug-in built for non technical decision-makers.

Greenvale (Agricultural tech startup)

PROJECT: STATISTICAL ANALYSIS ON CROP YIELD DATA

Cambridge, United Kingdom Aug 2019 - Jan 2020

- Conducted statistical analysis on crop yield data to examine seasonal effect on tuber growth across varieties.
- Developed a short-term forecasting model using Gaussian Processes for canopy development based on groundcover observations.

Bonmarché (Fashion retail), UK

London, United Kingdom

PROJECT: MARKDOWN PRICE OPTIMISATION

Mar 2019 - May 2019

- Developed a demand forecasting model to predict pre-markdown sales and solved for the optimal discount and markdown price to reach the user-defined target sell-through.

Advisory Position

Hop3 Rewards

California, United States

Data Science Advisor

Jan 2023 - Present

- Advise the data science development in hop3, a web 3.0-powered rewards app that reinvents the way people find fun things to do and interact with brands.

Juvenate Consulting

Hong Kong

Advisor

Jan 2019 - Jan 2021

- Advised in the early-stage developement in Juvenate, a student-led consultancy striving for greater social impact while helping young people acquire essential skills in the workplace.